Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Katherine and today
we have a very painful lesson for you.
That's right, today we're going to
go to one of the worst places for me.
We're going to go to the dentist.
Okay, so the person in this dialogue has
a pain in their mouth in the tooth area.
So let's take a listen to
this dialogue and when we
come back we'll be talking
a little bit more about it.
What seems to be the problem?
I have a really bad toothache. My
cheek is swollen and I can't eat anything.
Let's have a look.
Mmm, this doesn't look too good. I think
we may have to pull out your wisdom tooth.
It's pressing against
your molars and that's one
of the reasons you're
experiencing so much pain.
When you pull my tooth, will you also
have to extract the nerve and the root?
First we will take some x-rays
and see what we're dealing with.
I also noticed a small cavity up front
here, so you are going to need a filling.
I guess that's what I get for not flossing
or brushing my teeth three times a day.
It could be that, or maybe
you are eating too many sweets.
In any case, I'll administer an
anesthetic and you won't feel a thing.
All right, we're back and obviously
we're going to take a look at a lot of
vocab related to going to the dentist
and experiencing a little bit of pain.
So let's take a look at
that in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Okay, first up in language takeaway
today we have the root of the problem.
It's a toothache.
That's right, we have
a really bad toothache.
Okay, well, egg means pain or
soreness and tooth is your tooth,
so I could say, "Oh gosh, I
have a really bad toothache."
That's right, that means
your tooth or your teeth hurt.
And basically you can combine it like a
stomach ache or headache, back ache.
That's right, so usually when
you have a tooth ache, you
experience different symptoms,
different things happen to you.
What's one of these things, Marco?
Well, in this case, the girl had a
swollen cheek, her cheek is swollen.
Ouch, so the cheek is the side of the face.
It's usually where it's a little bit pink.
And when your cheek
is swollen, it looks puffy.
It looks bigger than normal.
That's right, so for example,
sometimes you fall and you hurt
your finger and it'll get fat
and it'll get puffy as you say.
It's swollen.
That's right, so anything
can be swollen really.
When you hit your toe on something hard and
your toe later gets bigger, it's swollen.
That's right.
So obviously her cheek is swollen
and she has a tooth ache because
apparently her wisdom teeth or
her wisdom tooth is coming out.
All right, so wisdom
teeth are special teeth.
I don't know if they
actually have anything to do
with wisdom, which means
being smart to be wise.
But wisdom teeth are those four teeth
in the very, very, very back of your mouth.
That's right, so these
are the last teeth that
come in or the last teeth
that grow in your mouth.
So I think usually you're
18 or 20 when they come in.
That's right, a lot of people
experience these when they're older.
Maybe that's why they call them wisdom
teeth because you're older and you're wiser.
I had them when I was about 14 or 13.
I was very young, but
these come in in the
very back, the furthest
away from your lips.
Okay, very good.
So when they come in, sometimes
there's not enough space and
so they start to press against
the other teeth in your mouth.
Specifically against your molars.
So molars are other teeth.
These are also in the back of your mouth.
You can tell which ones are molars,
I believe, because they're flat on top.
They look like a little square.
Those are the ones that you
used to chew your food with mostly.
Exactly, they're not
pointy like your front teeth.
And so molars are in
the back of your mouth.
Wisdom teeth are in the
very back of your mouth.
And molars can be very sore when
the wisdom teeth push against them.
And so in this case, you
will have to take your
teeth out or the dentist
will take your teeth out.
But what's something we say when we
talk about taking the whole tooth out?
Well, in this case, he's
going to extract the tooth,
but also he's going to
extract the nerve and the root.
Okay, so nerves are parts of our bodies.
We can't see them, but
they help us feel things.
So maybe when someone
hits me, the nerves
in my arm, they tell
my brain that it hurts.
Well, we also have nerves in our teeth,
and that's what we're talking about here.
But what's this other thing?
You talked about the nerve and the root.
It's very similar to a plant, for example.
You're considered that
your teeth are like plants,
and they have little roots
that go into your gums.
And this is how basically
you get teeth stay alive.
They are fed basically by your body.
All right, so root, like with a tree or a
plant, is the very bottom of something.
In this case, to extract means
to take out or to take away.
So the dentists will have to
extract the root and the nerve.
That sounds pretty painful.
It's painful, but they
have to do it, right?
So when the dentist has
to extract the tooth, in
this case, the nerve and
the root and everything,
in order for you not to feel
it, he gives you special drugs.
What are these drugs called?
These are called anesthetics.
Okay, so most people, when they are
having major surgery, they get anesthetics,
so that they can't feel anything.
Remember, we were
just talking about nerves.
Well, anesthetics make it so that you
can't feel things through your nerves.
That's right.
So obviously, you don't
want to feel the pain when
somebody's pulling that
tooth out of your mouth.
So you get an anesthetic, and
then you don't really feel anything.
You kind of feel something,
but you don't really feel pain.
Exactly.
So anesthetic basically makes you numb.
Numb, that's right.
That's the word numb.
Okay, so we're taking a look at a lot
of vocab, molars, wisdom, teeth, etc.
Why don't we listen to the dialogue again,
and we'll be back in a
bit with Fluency Builder.
What seems to be the problem?
I haven't really bad toothache.
My cheek is swollen,
and I can't eat anything.
Let's have a look.
Mmm, this doesn't look too good.
I think we may have to
pull out your wisdom tooth.
It's pressing against your
molars, and that's one
of the reasons you're
experiencing so much pain.
When you pull my tooth, will you also
have to extract the nerve and the root?
First, we will take some x-rays
and see what we're dealing with.
I also noticed a small cavity up front
here, so you are going to need a filling.
I guess that's what I get for not flossing
or brushing my teeth three times a day.
It could be that, or maybe
you are eating too many sweets.
In any case, I'll administer an
anesthetic, and you won't feel a thing.
All right, so the topic of
today's lesson is toothache,
but it's also basically about learning that
you will have to have your tooth taken out.
So, to say, as we say, to pull out a tooth.
Okay, so that's what the dentist said.
I think we may have to
pull out your wisdom tooth.
They're not good news.
Okay, so to pull out means to extract.
So, just remember here,
this is a phrase that has
pull out to out would
be the preposition here.
We wouldn't say pull off or pull out.
We'd say pull out.
Like, for example, you can
pull out a hair or your hair.
Exactly.
Okay, so we're pulling out the
wisdom tooth, and the dentist
first wants to take some x-rays
to see what we're dealing with.
Okay, so to deal with something means to
work on it or to have something to do with.
And so, in this case, an dentist
wants to know, is this serious?
What are we dealing with here?
That's right.
And so, he's trying to judge the situation.
So, maybe what would be
another scenario or another situation
when you would say, I have
to see what we're dealing with.
Well, in the case of the weather and the
newsmen who report about the weather,
maybe they see that a storm is
coming, but they have to look at the
radars and the computer screens
to see what they're dealing with.
Is it a serious storm or
is it a very weak storm?
They have to evaluate.
That's right.
Okay, very good.
And so, we're going to
see what we're dealing with.
And then the girl, I think, knows that she
hasn't really taken good care of her teeth.
And so, she says, I guess that's what I
get for not flossing or brushing my teeth.
So, that's what you
get, or that's what I get.
Here, the pronoun changes.
I, you, he, that's what I get
for not taking care of myself.
This means it's my fault.
I deserved it.
I deserved this thing.
So, I could say, Marco, that's what
you get for not doing your homework.
You got a bad grade on your test.
That's right.
So, it's basically a way of
saying, that's what you deserve.
That's the consequence for your actions.
Exactly.
Okay.
And what about our last phrase?
One thing that I hate to hear from doctors
and dentists, because usually it's a lie.
A dentist will say, before
he gives you a shot, or
before he takes your tooth
out, you won't feel a thing.
That's right.
So, he's basically saying,
you're not going to feel any pain.
But why do we say, you won't feel a
thing instead of you won't feel anything?
Just a set phrase.
Is it something we say,
I would remember it like
this, because it's more
likely to be said in this way.
You won't feel a thing.
I think it basically means
not even one little thing.
You're not going to feel that.
So, for example, I'm about
to fix someone's back.
You know, and you have to pull
them and make their back feel better.
I say, you won't feel a thing.
You fix their back.
Okay.
So, you won't feel a thing,
or you won't feel anything.
Both are correct, but I think it's more
common to hear, you won't feel a thing.
Okay, so why don't we
go back, let's take one last
look at our dialogue,
and we'll be back in a bit.
What seems to be the problem?
I haven't really bad toothache.
My cheek is swollen,
and I can't eat anything.
Let's have a look.
Mmm, this doesn't look too good.
I think we may have to
pull out your wisdom tooth.
It's pressing against your
molars, and that's one
of the reasons you're
experiencing so much pain.
When you pull my tooth, will you also
have to extract the nerve and the root?
First, we will take some x-rays
and see what we're dealing with.
I also noticed a small cavity up front
here, so you are going to need a filling.
I guess that's what I get for not flossing
or brushing my teeth three times a day.
It could be that, or maybe
you are eating too many sweets.
In any case, I'll administer an
anesthetic, and you won't feel a thing.
All right, so talking about
dentists and talking about wisdom
teeth, you say that you still
have all four wisdom teeth.
I do, they're all still back there.
So, you didn't need to have
them take it out, or pulled.
No, as my dentist
likes to say, I have a big
mouth, which in English
has two meanings.
A big mouth is not just a large mouth,
but also it means you like to talk a lot.
Right.
So, but did you ever have braces,
for example, when you were a kiss?
Oh, you had braces.
I had a retainer,
which is a device that
you, it looks like a
line across your teeth,
and you put it in usually
at night, but sometimes
during the day, and it makes
some space in your mouth.
But I also had braces after that.
I hated braces.
I had them for two years.
Why did you hate braces?
Because they're uncomfortable.
Well, they don't look very good,
especially when you're a 13 year old girl.
And you want to look cute, and you
have this big metal thing in your mouth.
That's right.
Did you have braces?
I had braces. Actually, it
was kind of, for a while, I
think a lot of people thought
it was cool to have braces.
I did not grow up with you grew up.
It was not cool.
I don't know.
I think, or it gets to a
point where in certain parts,
I guess my school was filled
with kids that had braces.
So, I guess everyone
just had really bad teeth.
So, obviously, the people that didn't
have braces kind of were left aside.
So, you're like, "Oh, I want braces.
I want to be part of the group.
" Kind of like, sometimes I wish I had
glasses, because everyone I know has glasses.
Really?
Yeah.
It's a vision, though.
Yeah, it sucks to be perfect, right?
Well, this is a really
interesting topic, and
going to the dentist
is always complicated.
Maybe some of our listeners
are dentists themselves,
or they have some stories
that you can share with us.
Please let us know what
you're thinking, and share
your dentist stories with
us on EnglishPod.com.
We're waiting for you there.
Alright, we'll see you guys then.
Bye.